so would you
say that the SOA
pner is perfectly self
transparent yeah that's where a
s the right view is a basically self
transparency to the sufficient extent
mhm yeah
and and that's basically culmination of
yeah yeah well the out of complete
culmination is
arhh when there's absolutely no no
contradiction left within you um but
that's what would have meant by the
um little dust in their eyes more Dust
In Their
Eyes whether is
basically transparent means you see
through clearly there is nothing obscuring
clearly there is nothing obscuring
it's not L if you're not as transparent
you have some Dust In Your Eyes so you
cannot quite See Clearly
mhm um there someone with a little bit of
um there someone with a little bit of
dust in their eyes means they could
still hear him yeah they could still
recognize what he was talking about well
the ones with a little dust in their
eyes yeah they would they would need
just fewer prompts towards uh that oh
developing that transparency that
recognition of the certain Universal
principles understanding those
understand in the nature of things to
the fundamental to their own
existence and that's
it there's nothing else that's being
obscured then you have those with more
Dust In Their Eyes they need to invest
more effort into developing their
transparency um so the really the question is what
um so the really the question is what
transparency is yeah exactly how does
some if that's what is self transparency
what is self and see that is uh devel in
self transparency is a
transparency is a
thread of practice of effort that is in
common yeah to somebody who's PJ and
somebody who's even
aruh so if putuj starts to develop uh
self transparency he's heading towards
the Right View even if he doesn't
necessarily know it the extent of his
transparency is sort of that's what's
in common at least the idea of the
direction that that's worth developing
yeah and that's why some people in the
sutas when they met the Buddha literally
just heard one sentence from him and
became fully enlightened cuz they've
actually removed everything else they
was obscuring it theyve developed that
transparency to degree necessary so
that's the that's the kind of That's the
basis of the Buddhist teaching the
practice if you want to if you're
interested in practicing according to
what the Buddha was talking about then
it's all within this idea
of becoming transparent yeah
understanding your motives
yeah toting I was going to ask you that
now so
what what is the definition of
transparent and non-transparent what's
the difference what would be a
different um characteristic of it that
you could differentiate these two things
so somebody who's transparent has is
clear about their motives yeah so
transparent in regard to what
transparent in regard to motivation
motivation for what well motivation for
bodily action for verbal action for
mental action yeah hence the the entire
teaching is is is bound and contained
within that nature of action and freedom
from it what am I doing so it's not like
I'm not transparent in regard to such
and such thing that I don't understand
that's not the transparency we talk
about yeah it's transparency in regard
to your own present here and now pretty
much whatever you're doing thinking
saying yeah transparency in regard to
motivation yeah that's like the most encompassing
yeah that's like the most encompassing
General way you could describe it it's
kind of could you say it's like yes it's
not being clear about everything but
just being far from it far from it but
just being because there are things that
are not clear that's the nature exactly
but it's being clear about the direction
you're heading in yeah it's being it's
being cleared it's it's about being
clear about um actions you're intending
you're about to intend actions you
intended and it's just the the kind of
vague direction of those actions like
like it might I say vague it might be it
might you might not be able
to I could say not everything is clear
but you just know at this direction
is yeah the content yeah the like oh
like shall I do this or
that I have an option A and option b so
I can investigate the option A see the
drawbacks of option b I can look at the
draw but all of that is kind of
secondary to what I'm talking about yes
you want to see why are you considering
doing either option A or option b
regardless of the results of option A
and option b so even if you cannot see
any drawback in an option
A but you still recognize that it's
purely rooted in your desire for
pleasure that's it you shouldn't do it
cuz that's more important where the
action is rooted the more you reflect
and contemplate that the more
transparent in regard to your own
motivation that it's there while you
want to commit the action you will
become in other words it will take you
less and less effort to see where the
action is rooted in greed diversion
delusion or non- greed non aversion non
delusion the more you invest uh into
seeing it
so like for for a late person for
example who who is not in the
environment of of the
um sens like sens strain of a monk or or
or somebody who has kind of renounced
the world but who wants to practice the
DH so like the absolute beginner so to
speak um even that it's the same
principle you want to be
clear for the
reasons clear about the reasons that are
making you act in that direction or in
this direction choosing this choosing
that and that applies to any form of
action not just immediate one I'm about
to do now but even my future plans mhm
so like that's that's another thing
so as a lay person oh I want to practice
DH why why do I want to practice
DH because I want to be free from
suffering okay that's a good answer so
where is that suffering that I want to
be free from
mhm is that suffering in the future so
I'll practice them in the future or is
that Li ability to suffering in the
present well it's in the present so how
does that level suffering in the present
manifest to me really
well through me experiencing unwanted
things through my own
actions so you want to practice dhama in
the future when you get your conditions
ready while in reality all you need to
do is start recognizing where your
motivation is rooted and you'll be
practicing D for the same purpose of
being free from suffering
mhm so you you recognize that can you
suffer in any way if you don't want
anything if you don't want to have
anything and you don't want to keep
anything no and you don't care about
losing anything or you don't care about
gaining anything can you experience any
discrepancy that would result in
suffering so can you then suffer if you
don't have any desire
whatsoever and emotional investment
whatsoever so then you realize whenever
you do suffer it's because you're
emotionally in invested and means
whenever you're emotionally invested
means you act out of that as your reason
yes more pleasure I don't want pain I
want a distraction I don't want not I
don't want like a nothingness neutral
feeling and so you're you're acting out
of that
desire is just simply keeping the whole
thing going yeah yeah you're you're
sustaining it you're maintaining it
you're feeding it so the trans the
transparency and again can you develop
transparency in regard to your
motivation if you don't even restrain
your actions if you're physically sort of
actions if you're physically sort of
already fully rooted in desire and
acting towards more desire no because
those actions are still yeah they're
keeping it well exactly exactly they're
fully rooted in that so it doesn't
matter how much you might try to
mentally resist the fact that you're
bodily engaging with with things that
routin desire means you you are fully
within that
I guess I guess like that's the thing
people the practice isn't some kind of
like something that's separate from your
life like you know oh I just live my
life like this and then all right now
I'll do some practice exact that's
completely got nothing to do with
basically if you do practice rightly it
will undermine your life it will start
undoing your life undoing your very Bava
your very being CU your life your life
is everything that you're doing which is
determined by your and when the word
speaks about the truth and seeing the
truth and so on it's not the truth you
know a secret that you haven't known
it's the truth in regard to your own
experience where my actions are rooted
so you can actually
recognize um what you said earlier on
that there are certain things are
unknown cannot be known mhm cannot be
empirically sort of verified yeah in
this life and that's a fact that or even
can be but they're not right now exactly
so right now what is empirically
verifiable is that these things cannot
be empirically verified exactly and you
recognize that and you realize and the way the
that and you realize and the way the
reason why you can recognize that is
because you realize it was never the
point of figuring these things out the
point was simply to not maintain greed
diversion delusion not maintain desire
on the level of Body Action speech
action mental action and that's it then
you don't have a problem with not
knowing things or haven't figured them
long enough cuz you you stop stop
assuming that the answer is at the end
of those things and you start to see
that actually your attempts to try to
find out about these things exactly
that's already rooted in something and
if you don't ignore that that's the
lacking of Truth not in like lacking of
um experiencing like certain content or
certain answers of your
experience so that's what I mean like
even when people do a meditation
technique that obviously will involve
this kind of time and then result of
some special experience they ignorant of
their motivation throughout yeah because
if you become aware you don't need a
technique yeah that's the field where
any effort
applies the field of motivation behind
me wanting to go a treat to do this
technique or do that technique why oh CU
I want to be free from suffering what is
free from suffering for me is it do I
assume it's some sort of experience
whereby everything else will be canceled
by
it or is it something else perhaps have
I investigated long enough to see so
that's the the clearer you are for about
your motives the clearer you will become
about what your goal is as well
MH that's why the Buddha talked about
the mundane Right View which is
recognizing there is good action there
is bad action that literally means ah so
there's a difference like it by the way
action can be same externally yeah but
there is a difference whether that
action is rooted in absence of Desire
absence of greed a verion delusion or is
it rooted in greed div verion delusion
you do the same thing externally it's
two different actions because you stop
judging action by the content you start
seeing it by the motivation behind which
are it's necessary presently enduring
roots that that's the thing so I was
always struck by the fact
that the common sense tells you that
you've got an action we so you're
talking about like observing an action
externally so that person is walking
over there and that person is also
walking over there so they're doing the
same thing externally the same action
it's not but they're doing it for
different reason he's going over there
to get away from something and he's
going over there CU he wants something
whatever so you distinguish them between
the act the action the external action
and the motivation and what you're
saying is motivation is more important
but actually the Buddha says the action
is the motivation they're not two
different things so actually to talk
about the external
Act is kind of well that's not even an
action yeah that's what I mean so that's
why he said
CH is what the action is action no
that's what I'm saying like it's
not like what you describe is the common
sense yeah common sense that's not what
action is exactly yeah so
so yeah every action is intention yeah
so your intention is your action even if
you don't make physically uh discernable
visible by others action yeah you're
already committed to that action through
your intention so everyone's measure of
this extern interal action oh this is
what he does and we can observe
externally that's it's measuring the
results of action yeah yeah yeah yeah
it's measuring that which is basically
rooted in that which is which is if you
think that's what action is you're not
going to see what action really is which
is the intention that binds it all like
throughout so to speak yeah to think of
the intention as the container of all
the acts by Body speech and mind you do
within that context of
intended result and
Consequence the the example an example
that V nanava came up with in his early
writings was you you some you make
someone's drinking a cup of tea and they
they put a spoonful of sugar into their
tea and you're watching this and you
know that that's arsenic so you think
why why is he killing
himself so you your measure for what it
is this external what's going on out
there yeah but that's not the act
because he doesn't know it's arsenic
people are when people are not aware of
their own motivation then they start
assuming motivation of others simply
based on the observing of the external
acts and we spoke about in other talks
where somebody would have unacceptable
speech and people would just assume ill
will and anger and conceit yet he's in
another hand
yeah and you will be much more kind of
prolific in the to the in the extent of
that assuming other people's motivation
the more you are unaware of your own
Yeah the more you become aware of your
own well the more accurate in Reading
other becomes without needing to assume
it yeah because now you know you're
becoming familiar with how motivation
works really so that's what I mean the
action is not what you've done the
action is the intention within which is
something you've done yeah so again back
that's why it's a mundane Right View
yeah it's because it's already aligning
itself with what the right view is yeah
you start recognizing where the work is
where the importance is you start recog
in the criteria what for what is
wholesome and for what is UNH wholesome
and that criteria for people is external
when they start it's all you shouldn't
do that you must do this doesn't matter
why yeah you just must adhere to this
form to this method to this technique
and then it's right it's not you can
adhere to the technique to rest of your
life for completely wrong reasons and
that's why you will not even have a
mundane Right View yeah let alone be
free from suffering so yeah so and the
important thing is this mundane Right
View it's not it's mundane it's like
it's it's um it's not mundane like
common no but it's but it's more like it
doesn't pertain to that Universal from
suffering you could say there are even
there are people who have no interest in
D and are closer to the mundane right
because are straightforward in
thear because the thinking does not
violate the basic principles of that
like Universal nature of things yeah
they're looking at what they're doing
why am I doing that's the whole the
whole thing the whole thing of that
description that mundan right view like
there is given there's all these things
means exactly that oh things are rooted
not in what you observed yeah but things
are rooted in basically motivation
behind it now as I said many times
before certain things externally done
always have to be rooted in certain
intentions such as killing stealing
cheating uh whatever sexual intercourse
from the point of view of of of of a
celibate person and so on you abandon
that but everything else is determined
by the intention behind not by the
content of what you're doing so like
there is Mother there is Father there is
good there is bad there is
responsibility for my own actions as in
oh responsibility for me walking sitting
talking doing this is on me not on the
reasoning that I have towards the world
so to speak when people say oh well no I
went there because such and such said so
that I should do it yeah you might do
that you might choose for that to be the
reason for your action but you will not
be able to ignore that you respons
responsible for choosing that such and
such person said something and that was
your reason for going you can always say
no to it
exactly so yeah so the the this the
usual state of affairs is someone places
authority over their life over what they
do or people induce that in personal
Authority because it helps them
alleviate that responsibility tell me
what to do oh I do that because that's
what we do here that's what we do in
this Society that's what we do in this
culture no you choose to do what the
society does or you choose to uh not do
what I could always say no to that I
could always say no to the group exactly
so the point is not to like go with the
group or against the group or either you
should always say no to the group yeah
the point is to recognize that you're
responsible for whatever you choose to
do exactly whether I say yes or no it's
my choice and you
cannot abstain from choosing they will
then abstain you from responsibility for
your choice because saying I will not
choose is your choice my choice is to
abstain from Choice a and choice B oh so
you're responsible for abstaining from
Choice a and choice B yeah so why would
why do people then avoid responsibility
for Choice it's
unpleasant it fills them with primordial
perfect form of duka duka literally
means opposite of Suka means this e or
un EAS it's not you know suffering and
despair of the world no it's that
uneasiness in regard to everything yeah
because literally everything that you
experience is of that Universal nature
of it's not in my control and that's why
it makes me
uneasy so you can you have two ways of
going about it either pretend it's not
there ignore it mhm which you can only
do as a starting point so to speak we
all start by ignoring the duka ignoring
the universal truth of that nature yeah
which then obviously results in
everything else the the self view
craving desire lust that then fuels it
even more so can we say like so sat
would have called that bad faith yeah
yeah it's a form of Faith like literally
you have thing right in front of your
face and you pretend it's not there I
believe that this that this it's not
there so it's already Your Existence
it's already a contradiction in terms I
believe that these things they were
given to me my feelings have aison for
me perceptions have a reason for me I
believe I have created them by being the
master and controller yet you have no
say in them but you still while not
having say in these things you feel you
still maintain the notion that you are
the owner of what you
feel and then you ignore everything else
that would contradict that
ownership and that's why duka cannot
enter you you cannot be liable to it
expose to it unless you make yourself so
mhm so through ignoring but obviously
there lack of control lack of safety
lack of
easiness that's why you become subjected
to lack of safety that's why you become
unsafe and uneasy and so
on and the reason you ignore it is
because it's
unpleasant but because of that you
experience even more unpleasure yeah
this great mass of suffering is the word
would say so you realize oh so you have
no choice about this pleasure you have
only choice about how much of it and you
realize well if I actually accept this
which now seems worse the the the
displeasure of anxiety and uneasiness
and lack of control and endure it I'm
actually overcoming all the other
suffering that will be as a result of
avoiding this
mhm hence even as a mundane right view
of a pug you would be doing already
undoing a lot of already removing a lot
of dust from your eyes a lot of wrong
views and other dependences on Greed
diversion and
delusion so suffering is right there
liability to suffering is right there as
I said would you be able to experience
any form of suffering any form of Pain
any form of
discomfort if you don't have a desire
for anything you gain gain or anything
you lost no so then if the only reason you
lost no so then if the only reason you
give to desire is to be free from pain
yet desire is the reason for any form of
pain why don't you just abandon the
desire and thus you abandon the pain cuz
that is your goal all along right from
the start the the worst ass without any
inclination to practice the dharm and
the best the purest the greatest of the
adans same motivation to be free from
Pain mhm is just how they go about
it trying to avoid it or yeah not not
appropriating so the transparency we
talk about then is about undoing these
contradictions that you carry already
within yourself that are making you
liable to suffering it's not about
figuring out the truth at the end of
your Meditation Retreat that would then
result in cancellation of all the
contradictions and the problems that
make you
suffer there are I mean there are lots
there are kind of more there are grosser
types of bad faith that people will well
bad faith is as endless as a VJ is cuz
that's what a VJ is so for example
someone might in order to ignore
something to turn a blind eye to it you
need to know that there is at least that
thing there yeah you cannot ignore that
which does not exist yeah yeah that's
the way of thing you're kind of lying to
yourself but how can you lie to yourself
cuz you know yeah well yeah that's
exactly how that's why people suffer
that's why people suffer account of what
other people say or do because it would
remind them of the stuff they're trying
to cover up
forsel if you're free from any form of
existential cover up there is nothing
that can provoke you or engage you or
affect you
you
nothing if you don't crave safety how
could you possibly suffer on kind of
lack of safety if you don't crave
control if you don't imply control if
you don't assume control how can you
suffer on account of random things
happening to
you and by the way when I say control I
don't mean controlling the world or the
things I mean people assume control over
their own feelings while at the same
time simultaneously they know they have
no say in those feelings arising they
know they're subjected to it but even
that recognition of I'm subed to feeling
they put within their Assumption of
control yeah they get the order on EX
the order exactly and that's why often
the Buddha would ask people who would
have approach them like that ah so you
are in control of which feeling is then
in your control is it Pleasant or is it
Pleasant or the the neutral one because
they there always one of them can only
be present not all of them yeah so if if
you are in the control of pleasant
feeling how come then it changes into
unpleasant one if you're in control of
unpleasant how come it changes into
neutral yeah that's say we need sort of
you can be reminded that yeah no
actually I'm not in control of these
feelings yeah and the reason why people
avoid such reminders is cuz they're
unpleasant yeah so you trying to outrun
discomfort of certain recognitions
within yourself is basically you trying
to control your feelings yeah you think
you are in a position to outrun that
which you're subjected to yeah you
ignoring it you're turning a blind eye
to it you're pretending it's not there
you're trying to cover up with a set of
feelings you
want so you're kind of living a
contradiction yeah well that's what Baba
is Bava is a contradiction you remove
the contradiction existence is ceased is
contradiction free yeah the transparency
Begins by
acknowledging the contradictions and and
like you said by round
themer exactly exactly yeah but most
people I mean it's just so you recognize
what's what's what's the first what
would be the most common
contradiction of of say a person want
start practicing the Dharma the
contradiction they have to start saying
no to
conflict have to start say no to yeah to
start rounding it up start abstaining
from precepts
exactly so here you are wanting to
develop freedom from suffering on
account of prac from the Dharma yeah and
um and I'm still doing this yeah so I
want to develop basically the strength
of mind yeah that will be immovable yeah
in regard to anything that I might be
subjected to but in the meantime I will keep
to but in the meantime I will keep
acting out of my weakness in order to
develop strength yeah that's a
contradiction in terms yeah like you
want to heal your richy skin infected
whatever ulcers that are very itchy you
have to stop start scatching and making
it worse as simple as that you still
don't know necessarily what the actual
cure might be but you already know you
should stop making it worse M cuz one
thing for sure even if you find the cure
later on it won't work cuz you destroyed
your whole arm with your
scratching so you already know that
certain types of behavior are rooted in
being unable to control yourself unable
to restrain yourself yet here you are
practicing for the ultimate immovability
the ultimate kind of restraint in regard
to giving into pain giving into pleasure
giving into anything that move you want
peace on account of which you keep
disturbing yourself yeah you basically
want to you're looking for freedom from
ill will from sense desire and yet you
give into ill will and sense desire you
want to be free from you're
acting that's what I mean like if both
sensual craving desire and ill will were
not originally and fundamentally
unpleasant you wouldn't be feeling
pressured to deal with it deal with it
yeah and that's what will said those act
those those those um those
experiences are always underlined by
that craving by more of that
craving and that's how you know that you
are precious yeah and and so like you
might crave for pleasure but the only
reason you crave for that Central
pleasure is because simultaneously
underneath it you crave crave for
freedom from the current in yeah yeah so
the context of me is I don't want this
pain of not having that thus AL C for
for that
yeah so it's what you're craving towards
it it's underlined by even more craving
they are both simultaneously there and
one feeds the other
yeah but looking at this thing that
you're heading towards allows you to
ignore exactly and allows you like that
hope that that will be the Escape of
this current pain yeah that's why the
sity on the level of assumption that's
the gratification that's the
gratification not getting it but hoping
that get it will free you from it and
that's why sensuality is the Assumption
as I said it's not deriving pleasure
from sense object is not but sensuality
is yeah it's assuming that pleasure
simultaneously craving for avoiding the
pain of not having it hence it's on the
level of a
view yeah so the first contradiction a
lay person has to undo is the
contradiction of uh lack of restraint
contradiction of not keeping the
precepts that's a contradiction to your
WR goal of wanting to practice the DH
yeah like ask yourself like even if
you're not sure well first you have to
be you have to read the sutas and become
familiar with what the actual goal of
dharm is but say even you're somewhere
in between you're unclear ask yourself
what enlightenment would what would
Enlightenment entail for me yeah that's
it that's what I was thinking I think
think there's so many contradictions you
can think of
that apply for and By
ignoring or by not making effort to
develop Clarity in regard to these
things you are
automatically maintaining contradiction
you don't need to make the effort to oh
I'll I I'll keep this contradiction all
you need to do is ignore it and that's
how you're keeping it
so I say it's quite common the idea of
so I want to practice for
enlightenment and yet Enlightenment is
this thing that will happen to
me um out of my control out of my
control if I do these things if I this
thing here then something I'll luy other
will suddenly happened to me yeah so
that's already the first thing you
should start questioning yeah well you
might want to believe that that's how
Enlightenment works but then if you read
the sutas you realize that's not what
the would have said well done reading
suit so most people probably don't read
the suts so I want to practice as the I
want I think the Buddhas probably answer
something but I won't find out I won't
find know that's another contradiction
so I want to practice the buddh teaching
but I also don't want to make the effort
to find out what they teaching clearly
is I'll just hope that these other
people that talk about so that's another
lack of transparency yeah yeah and that
will also prevent you from being clear
about your own motives but if you start
investigating your motives as I said
your goal will become clearer if your
goal of practic and D is clearer then it
will make obvious sense to invest effort
in finding out what that d i
is but even if you're not there even
though it's even though it's quite a
difficult thing to do there's so many
books there so many things to read but
start to start that shouldn't stop me
exactly means like oh yeah okay so
that's the extent of the work that needs
to be done not like oh it's too much it
us I won't do any of it yeah it's not
that's just what and that's what what I
said many times like a person who
recognize what's for his own welfare as
in whether I engage with sensuality
whether I don't engage with sensuality
either way I
suffer which suffering can has greater
Prospect of resulting in sensation of
suffering engaging with sensuality and
prolonging desire or abstaining from it
so you already have the direction then
that person would go and find those who
teach abstaining from sensuality to
learn more about it then he would Ponder
on what they said then he would get a
sense of it having a sense of it then he
says he measures the task oh it becomes
clearer to him what needs to be
done when you know what needs to be done
he sets to do it and the reason why
people don't know what DH practice is
because they never made the effort to
really find out what their task is
yeah well unfortunately all the they
made was invested in the wrong direction
so that's the thing so people hope yeah
that just by listening to this talk on
YouTube or that will just spark in that
will give me all the knowledge I need
yeah yeah so you ask yourself what is what is
yeah so you ask yourself what is what is
Enlightenment for
me what do I think it is or I want
Enlightenment what do I want through
that Enlightenment what is the what is
the sort of what is the goal of it what
is the result of it is it permanent
pleasure okay permanent pleasure in what form
okay permanent pleasure in what form
like permanent Central pleasure or
permanent peaceful
pleasure I guess it's permanent peaceful
pleasure so what is the main
characteristic of the like permanent
peace ah it's absence of
disturbances absence of what
disturbances while absence of
disturbances that I know and see and
hear and smell and taste and touch and
are unable to be in different
toward so which is more likely then
would the perfect peace come as a result
of of you preventing smell smell taste
touch and all the other senses or would
perfect peace come as a result of you
learning how to be unmoved in regard to
smell sense and everything
else which one makes more
sense well being un move makes more
sense so why don't I start practicing
lack of moving in regard to things right
here right now that move me mhm he has
would that have a greater Prospect of
pertaining to Central that you already
value through your own random efforts
yeah but now it's not some random
anymore yeah you actually well reasoned
well contemplated and you're already
getting a sense of direction which means
you're already getting a sense of what
needs to be done yeah and what you're
doing there is clearer more transparent
exactly and doesn't depend on on other
people and doesn't depend on the
circumstances it's in regard to the
circumstances that's and that's the
whole point that's what the would said
whatever is to be obtained by oneself by
one manly effort manly strength manly
endurance I've obtained I'm an arant I'm
full enlightened arship is something you
enlightened arship is something you
developed not something that happens to
you and that's why it cannot be taken
away from you in the same sense Pleasant
feeling has arisen you're subjected to
it and then it disappeared it's taken
away from you yeah but if you developed
your mind in regard to manifestation in
regard to arising of anything feeling
perception intention sight sound smell
taste touch thought
whatever it's not dependent on the
content of it but it's dependent on your
attitude towards it yeah you realize you
will be immovable in regard to anything
and everything even the most extreme
examples that are listed in the sutas of
being killed and butchered and your mind
composure will not
change and that's possible because your
practice has ceased to pertain to the
circumstances to the senses but it
started looking at the nature of it in
regard to which you train your
immovability imperturbability and that training
imperturbability and that training
starts when you're completely unlight in
po you don't you don't magically slot
into it when you develop the Right View
you develop the Right View because
you've been training
rightly so can you
say so it's it's quite
common to I think for people to think
that practicing the dmer is evolved not
thinking involves kind of thinking
thinking is thinking is the problem yeah
you're always thinking these things just
yeah well the question you should
immediately ask yourself there
is so if it's just about doing it uh
what is the motivation for doing rooted
is it rooted in doing or is it rooted in
thought behind you doing yeah so that's
yet here you are ignoring thought on
account of you're doing means you ignore
the reason for motivation which means
you ignore what action is and somehow
you're hoping to free yourself from
action so basically
if someone wants to really start
practicing in line with the
dmer if they're not already which you
probably are if you're listening to
these videos but it's about kind of no I
do need to start thinking about my
motivation cuz that's the that where D
is
yeah my motivation for it is I'm not
justified in doing anything or not doing
anything I have no justification for
anything whatever I do whatever I choose
not to do it's cuz I made a choice for
which I'm responsible thus I'm not
justified or absolved from that
responsibility so I want to practice
dhama okay why oh because I want to be
from suffering okay why so what's
important is my responsibility I'm
responsible for what's important
basically recognizing that
responsibility not running away from it
not covering it up cuz it's unpleasant
accepting that uneasiness like you're
responsible yet you're not in control
it's a very uneasy situation literally
if I tell you oh if something happens to
such and such person if they do
something stupid you'll pay the price
yeah yeah that's basically what is what
responsible that's what Sara is that's
what existence is yeah yeah yeah that's
good way putting it you have to recog
recognizing that existential
responsibility is the Gateway for the
direction of the dharm yeah you can
spend 50 years practicing the dharm if
you haven't started that practice
through that Gateway there is no D in
your practice
and if that upsets you hearing that well
it just
confirms that you haven't developed
freedom from suffering you haven't
developed imperturbability in regard to
circumstances which is words of others
mhm like is my practice freeing me from
suffering not by controlling the
circumstances preventing the exposure to
things that might upset me but through
me being unable to move unable to suffer
unable to despair on account of things I
cannot Escape thus you will not need an
escape anymore as in in trying to outrun
s sounds Mel touches deny them through
refusing to think about him and so on
you cannot suffer either way that's
truly the burden oh I don't need to do
anything there's no burden for me when I
see this I must do this when I think
that I must run this way could could you
say that's the kind of that sense of
self is almost that's what it is it's
that escape it's that kind of
safety it's a product yeah of your
dependence on looking for that of the
assumption that there is some y some
yeah that's the direct product that's
what mean sense of self self is not a
problem it's a symptom yeah and you want
to approve that symptom well you stop
maintaining it to stop ignoring
Sankara uh being the duka and being an
and being duka as in being not in my
control and being uneasy you stop
ignoring non- contr control and
uneasiness you will stop aining this is
mine this is
myself even if you don't necessarily
think about oh now I must practice anata
anata will be the result of you not
supporting ATA through your own actions
and thinking and so
on so start undoing contradictions yeah
that's and that will result in Right
View and then that will result in arship
so the fundamental fundamental
contradiction sorry is will be said like
you don't need to chase down all the
contradictions in the world start with
the ones that are like more obvious to
you based on whatever faculties you have
but fundamentally bring them all home so
to speak what is the fundamental
contradiction of this
body well that I assume control over it
and yet I'm not in control of it yeah
the you and like the the life the
depends upon the operating body yeah can
that be in your control
yeah yeah is that is that the context
that you have at the back of your mind
throughout your day MH that you not in
control in your on your own body let
alone of your own life or is that a
context that you kind of drift away from
and forget about and
ignore that's all it takes you don't
need to make extra effort towards
ignorance all you need to do is ignore
the right thing that's how you're
investing in ignorance already all you
need to do is lose the sight of the
context that you're not in control of
this body if you lose that site automatically
body if you lose that site automatically
you're assuming control yeah
automatically you're acting out of GED
version delusion
so so it's not just so it's learning not
to tolerate contradictions but also
learning to recognize them because you
for for for so long you've allowed them
to be there without actually and you
will recognize them when you learn how
to endure them and not give in to
them yeah so when you learn to endure
the uneasiness
yeah and again the first uneasiness
you're going to get is the uneasiness of
starting to keep the presets and you
might you might first of all that those
contradictions might be gross might be
quite obvious but maybe that's why you need to
obvious but maybe that's why you need to
start but what saying is like well there
will be more deep rooted and if you
wonder where the contradictions are well
just ask yourself have you been acting
out of Desire recently have you
committed any act by Body speech or mind
out of desire that's your contradiction
already desire implies ownership implies
that result do you feel any shame yeah
do you see the danger that desire no
that's another contradiction cuz it's
dangerous yeah here you are riding on
this body as if you created it you're in
control yet you have no idea even how
components operate and if something
interferes with it that's it your ride
is gone yeah it's finished and you know
that that's why death is so terrifying
for people not because death is
terrifying itself but because you
literally your entire existence ignores
it the more you ignore it the more power
it has
so when that transparency is developed
sufficiently enough then literally
becomes obvious so is obvious that's why
Declaration of sa of course whatever has
the nature to manifest for that very
reason it's not in my control because
it's manifested that's why it will cease
nothing else and you just cultivate that same
else and you just cultivate that same
thing and any traces of any desire any
little contradictions or discrepancies
go